A Guide to the Papers of George E. Wagner 1861-1904
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of George E. Wagner 1861-1904
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11174
This collection contains 71 items (one Hollinger box).
This collection consists of papers of Lieutenant Colonel George Emil Wagner (1842-1904) of Philadelphia County, Pennsylvania, an officer of United States Colored Troops during the Civil War. Letters, military commissions, quartermaster returns, special orders and miscellaneous documents pertain to his career and service with the 88th Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry and the 6th, 8th and 9th regiments of United States Colored Troops, chiefly with the 88th Pennsylvania and the 8th USCT.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The George E. Wagner Papers were purchased by the Library from Christie's of New York on April 27, 1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
Wagner's military service is occasionally mentioned in the History of the 88th Pennsylvania Volunteers In The War For The Union, 1861-1865 (1894), which contains a postwar photograph of him. Wagner was mustered into the army in August 31, 1861 and his subsequent military career was a series of rapid promotions: first sergeant, Company D, 88th Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry January 1862; second lieutenant, 88th Pennsylvania, April 1862; first lieutenant, 88th Pennsylvania, December 1862; first lieutenant and adjutant, 5th Regiment, Veteran Reserve Corps, June 15, 1863; captain, 6th United States Colored Troops, August 25, 1863; captain, Company A, 8th USCT, October 13, 1863; captain and post adjutant, Company A, 8th USCT, 1864; major, 8th USCT, September 1864; lieutenant colonel, 9th USCT, October 1864; lieutenant colonel, 9th USCT, November 1864. He was discharged due to Olustee battle wounds on December 12, 1864 and awarded the brevet rank of colonel in March 1865. In 1889 Wagner delivered the keynote speech for the dedication of the 88th Pennsylvania's Gettysburg monument.
Prominent soldiers and civilians represented or mentioned in Wagner's papers include: William Birney (1819-1907), Loren Burritt, Benjamin Butler (1818-1893), Andrew Curtin (1817-1894), Ulysses Doubleday (1824- 1893), Benezet Foust (b. 1840), James A. Hardie (1823-1876), Andrew Johnson (1808-1875), Abraham Lincoln (1809-1865), George B. McClellan (1826-1885), Irvin McDowell (1818-1885), George P. McLean, William Reading Montgomery (1801-1871), Leonard Myers (1827-1905), Edwin Ord (1818-1883), James B. Rickett (1817-1888), Israel R. Sealy, James Shaw, Jr. (1830-1906), Edwin M. Stanton (1814-1869), Edward D. Townshend (1817-1893), Louis Wagner (b. 1838), and David Yulee (1810-1886).
Places or events discussed or described include contemporary events and issues such as military camp life, the battle of Gettysburg [1863], Fairfax Station, Virginia [August 8, 1863], the battle of Olustee, Florida [February 20, 1864; also known as Ocean Pond], the battle of Fort Gilmer [Chaffin's Farm/New Market Heights, September 28-30, 1864], and the occupation by Union troops of the Virginia cities and towns of Alexandria, Fredericksburg, Petersburg and Warrenton.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, 1861-1904, 71 items (one Hollinger box), consists of papers of Lieutenant Colonel George Emil Wagner (1842-1904) of Philadelphia County, Pennsylvania, an officer of United States Colored Troops during the Civil War. Letters, military commissions, quartermaster returns, special orders and miscellaneous documents pertain to his career and service with the 88th Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry and the 6th, 8th and 9th regiments of United States Colored Troops, chiefly with the 88th Pennsylvania and the 8th USCT. (The 8th was recruited and enrolled at Camp William Penn, Pennsylvania, between September 22 and December 4, 1864. From January 1864 to November 1865 this regiment served in Florida, Virginia, and Texas. Wagner apparently participated in the training of African-American Union soldiers at Camp Penn, the site of a specialized facility, the "Free Military School for Applicants for Command of Colored Troops" [December 1863 to September 1864] for the instruction of white Union officers designated for command of black troops.) However, with a few exceptions, there is little direct information in this collection about African-American soldiers.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject in six folders.
Organization
The folder Letters of George E. Wagner to Samuel H. Ritter (1861-1864, 1876 & 1904) consists of letters to his Philadelphia friend Ritter: "October 14, 1861 (with envelope), Camp Moore, Alexandria, Virginia"--writing as an orderly sergeant (88th Pennsylvania) GEW summarizes his regiment's journey from Philadelphia to Washington via Baltimore, the regiment's transfer to and description of secessionists in Alexandria, the regiment stationed at Fort Ellsworth and still awaiting muskets; "December 9, 1861, Alexandria, Virginia"--recounts GEW's visit to Wilmington [Delaware] and return to Alexandria, the accidental shooting of a second lieutenant during a whiskey search, and news of confiscation of property belonging to a brother of former Florida senator and Confederate Congressman David Yulee; "January 20, 1862, Alexandria"--Wagner defends Army of the Potomac General George B. McClellan's delay in attacking Richmond until the army is ready, disagrees with government handling of the Trent Affair [November 1861- January 1862], says the regiment was recently paid is plagued by "a large number of drunken & disorderly cases" and general unruliness in the camp, GEW's hopes for an officer's commission, a "Negro Troupe" as the only amusement, and a forthcoming grand ball to be attended by "professional" ladies
"February 12, 1862 (with envelope), Alexandria"--arrests of secessionist preachers who spoke defiance of military governor General William Reading Montgomery, the 88th Regiment ransacks and sets fire to a newspaper office in retaliation, a dispute among the regiment's companies as which could have their headquarters at Steward Church, and secessionists are forced to display Union flags at their residences and places of business
"March 25, 1862, Camp Kelly, District of Columbia"--scarcity of stationery had delayed his response to Ritter's letters, camp news, and rain every day the previous week; "May 24, 1862, Camp Curtin, Fredericksburg, Virginia"--GEW's promotion to lieutenant, passing references to various things (Mount Vernon, 90th Pennsylvania Volunteers), the resignation of Captain George W. Fairlamb, comments that Fredericksburg "ain't of much account [and] negroes are the principle population" and its townspeople hate Yankees, identifies the regiment as a member of the General James B. Rickett's brigade in General Edwin Ord's Division (26th and 94th New York and 88th and 90th Pennsylvania), complains of irregular mail delivery and reports that the was division reviewed on the previous day by Abraham Lincoln, Secretary of War Edwin Stanton and General Irvin McDowell; "November 9, 1862 (with envelope), Warrenton, Virginia"--GEW mentions General McClellan and rumors of his removal from command and speculates on the army's decline if true, he complains about ending of draft in Philadelphia and criticizes draftees, describes the hardships of winter camp life, his expectations of promotion to first lieutenant due to desertion of another lieutenant, and requests help in obtaining a civilian job as "I shall probably soon leave the service."
On "August 2, 1863, Rappahannock River, Virginia", GEW discusses the regiment's participation in the battle of Gettysburg where it captured the colors of two Confederate regiments (23rd North Carolina and 16th Alabama), a detail has been sent to Philadelphia to obtain conscripts to replenish the regiment's ranks, Captain W. H. Fairlamb deserted during the battle due to cowardice, discusses his plans to seek a commission in one of the Negro regiments being organized in Philadelphia, and briefly describes cavalry skirmish near Culpeper, Virginia [Fairfax Station; August 8, 1863]; "September 20, 1864 (with envelope), Petersburg, Virginia"-- Confederate shelling of his camp [GEW is now a member of the 8th United States Colored Troops], describes "hard duty" in the trenches, mentions the "Petersburg Express" ["The Dictator," a mammoth Union mortar used during the Petersburg siege], General Butler has promoted him to major, GEW's hopes Lt. Colonel Burritt will be promoted to colonel so that "this will make another opening" for yet another promotion.
"December 26, 1904"-- letter from Ritter to G. Ellwood Wagner mentions the death of George Wagner (Ellwood's father) and encloses as a gift ten of Wagner's wartime letters (three with envelopes addressed to Ritter, 14 October 1861, 12 February and 9 November 862) and four cartes-de-visites (not present). An unrelated item in this folder is an 1876 Pennsylvania Railroad special ticket number 7013 for travel from Pittsburgh to Philadelphia.
The folder Quartermaster Returns (1863-1864) concern Wagner's service as captain and post adjutant/quartermaster, Co. A, 8th United States Colored Troops, at Hilton Head, South Carolina, Olustee, Florida, and Camp William Penn, Chelten Hills, Pennsylvania. These "Monthly Return of Clothing, Camp and Garrison Equipage" are chiefly items transferred to and from First Lieutenant Willard R. Hammond, adjutant and post quartermaster, 6th United States Colored Troops, First Lieutenant Edwin B. Burrows, regimental quartermaster, 8th United States Colored Troops, Second Lieutenant William H. Brooks, 8th United States Colored Troops, Captain R. C. Bailey, 8th USCT, and First Lieutenant James R. Mulliken, 25th USCT. Issuance of clothing and equipment to musicians of Brigade Band No. 2, United States Colored Troops (1864 Jul 20, Jul 31, Aug 31), an October 1863 monthly quartermaster return signed November 2, 1863 by Wagner as first lieutenant, Company D, 88th Pennsylvania Infantry, "Camp in the Field, Virginia," and, his July 2, 1864 certification and itemization of 8th USCT equipment lost as a result of the Union's defeat at the battle of Olustee, Florida (February 20, 1864) are among these forms. A February 2, 1864 clothing allowance form signed by sixty-six members of Camp A, 8th United States Colored Troops is filed in this collection's oversize folder.
Items in the folder Special Orders and Medical Certificates (1863-1865) are primarily printed orders confirming Wagner's promotions, and certificates of disability (April 1864) or sick leave due to a gunshot wound in the hip during the battle of Olustee. These orders were issued by the Department of the South (Hilton Head, South Carolina) and the Department of Virginia and North Carolina; Wagner was granted a leave of absence in Philadelphia. Two 1863 printed form letters (August 25 and October 13) signed by Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton notifies Wagner of his promotions to captain in the 6th and 8th United States Colored Troops regiments. Special Orders No. 174 (May 11, 1864), signed by Assistant Adjutant General Edward D. Townshend (War Department, Washington, D. C.), orders Wagner to report for duty to Lieutenant Colonel Louis Wagner, 88th Pennsylvania, Camp William Penn, Philadelphia. Special Orders No. 282 (August 26, 1864), also signed by Townshend, relives Wagner of his Camp Penn duties and instructs him to rejoin his regiment; it bears two stamps: "Received Head Quarters Department of Susquehanna Aug. 29 1864" and on the reverse "Sep 5 1864." Special Orders No. 350 (November 14, 1864) grants Wagner twenty days of sick leave on account of his wounds; a November 16, 1864 receipt from Surgeon Nathan F. Blunt (11th Maine Infantry), "Base Hospital, Tenth Army Corps (Jones Landing, Virginia)," of Wagner's payment of seven dollars for room and board. An officers' hospital (Middle Department, Annapolis, Maryland) certificate reports Wagner as honorably discharged on December 14, 1864 and a Pension Office letter of February 24, 1865 informs him of his monthly pension of ten dollars.
One of the most interesting folders is Recommendation Letters, (1864-1866) from fellow officers of black Union regiments in support of Wagner's brevet promotion to colonel. They praise his gallantry and conduct at the battle of Olustee, Florida and were written by Colonel James Shaw, Jr., 7th United States Colored Troops (January 3, 1864); Lt. Colonel Loren Burritt, 8th United States Colored Troops (January 11, 1865 & December 26, 1866); Brigadier General William Birney, 2nd Division, 25th Army Corps, Army of the James (January 15, 1865); Colonel George P. McLean, 88th Pennsylvania Infantry (December 14, 1866); Brevet Brigadier General Benezet Foust, assistant commissioner, Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen and Abandoned Lands [Freedmen's Bureau], South Carolina (December 20, 1866). There are two letters from Colonel Ulysses Doubleday, 45th United States Colored Troops. On December 24, 1864 he writes: "If all our officers were like him [Wagner] our armies would be invincible"; on July 1, 1865 Doubleday urges Wagner's promotion to brevet brigadier general. In a June 4, 1866 printed form letter U.S. Army Inspector General James A. Hardie informs Congressman Leonard Myers that Wagner has been nominated for the brevet rank of colonel. Of special interest is Wagner's printed copy (signed in blue ink by Assistant Adjutant General Israel R. Sealy) of General Benjamin Butler's sixteen-page October 11, 1864 address to the Army of the James, recounting its heroics, especially United States Colored Troops regiments. Butler praises numerous officers and soldiers for gallantry, medal commendations and promotion. Major Wagner's promotion (Third Division, Tenth Army Corps) to lieutenant colonel, 9th United States Colored Troops, is on page sixteen. Also present is a blank officer's "Oath of Office" form.
Among the items in the folder Histories of the 8th United States Colored Troops are three undated autograph manuscripts, with corrections, presumably written by Wagner. These include "Eight Regiment U. S. Colored Troops" (8 pages in pencil) and an untitled, incomplete manuscript (pages 6-15, in ink) narratives of the 8th United States Colored Troops's service from its mustering in at Camp William Penn, Pennsylvania, its participation in the battle of Olustee, Florida, transfer to Virginia and the Army of the James, the battle of Fort Gilmer [Chaffin's Farm/New Market Heights, Virginia], the Petersburg Campaign, postwar service on the Texas-Mexico border, and mustering out at Camp Cadwalader, Pennsylvania, in December 1865. A third manuscript, "Some Account of the Services of the Eight Regt. U. S. Colored Troops/By one who served as an Officer with it, from its Organization to its Disbandment" (6 pages--incomplete, in ink) is a history of the 8th ending with its arrival at Jacksonville, Florida, on the eve of the Olustee battle. The fourth item in this folder is "Extract of Colonel Nelson B. Bartram's speech on the occasion of the presentation of the 20th United States Colored Troops's colors by the New York Union League" in which Bartram praises the 8th United States Colored Troops's bravery at Olustee and writes in a postscript: "Geo[orge] I thought the above would be good to introduce in your history of the 8th." The last item in this folder is a document of twelve "Questions for Col. Wagner" (on the reverse of a September 7, 1877 form letter of William Birney, United States attorney for the District of Columbia); these questions pertain to the 9th United States Colored Troops and the battle of Fort Gilmer on September 29, 1864. Birney inquires about his orders and actions and the location of Union generals David B. Birney, Benjamin F. Butler, Ulysses S. Grant, and James Shaw, Jr. Birney had become involved in controversy with Colonel James Shaw and Joseph M. Califf of the 7th United States Colored Troops. Califf was the author of Record of the Services of the Seventh Regiment(1878), in which he criticized Birney for failing to issue proper written orders during the regiment's recruitment, improper use of recruiting funds, and his faulty leadership at Fort Gilmer. An angry Birney accused Shaw and Califf of libeling his reputation, and Wagner's responses (not present) were undoubtedly used by Birney for his published defense General William Birney's Answer to Libels Clandestinely Circulated By James Shaw, Jr(1878). Wagner's August 10, 1878 letter to Shaw, reprinted on pages 6 and 7 of Califf's November 30, 1878 pamphlet rebuttal of Birney's accusations, To the Ex-Members And Friends of The 7th U.S.C.T., implies that during the battle Birney's incorrect assurances as to the security of the 8th Regiment's flanks, and his failure to resupply it with ammunition, nearly causing it to be surrounded and captured.
The collection's Oversize folder contains Wagner's military commissions, 1862-1866, signed by Pennsylvania Governor Andrew Curtin, General Benjamin F. Butler, President Andrew Johnson, and Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton.
Contents List
- Letters of George E. Wagner to Samuel H. Ritter 1861-1864, 1876, 1904, 11 items (Folder 1)
- Quartermaster Returns 1863-1864, 24 items (Folder 2)
- Special Orders and Medical Certificates 1863-1865, 13 items (Folder 3)
- Recommendation Letters 1864-1866, 11 items (Folder 4)
- Histories of the 8th United States Colored Troops [by George E. Wagner] 1864, 1877, 5 items (Folder 5)
- Commission, George E. Wagner, First Sergeant, Company D 88th Pensylvania Volunteers, signed, Colonel George P. McLean (Benezet F. Foust, adjutant), Alexandria, Virginia 1862 Jan 6 (Folder 6)
- Commission, George E. Wagner, Second Lieutenant, 88th Pennsylvania Volunteers, signed Governor Andrew Curtin, Harrisburg 1862 May 27 (Folder 6)
- Commission, George E. Wagner, First Lieutenant, Company D, 88th Pennsylvania Volunteers, signed Governor Andrew Curtin, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania 1863 Feb 25 (Folder 6)
- Clothing allowance form: "We, the undersigned Non-commissioned Officers, Artificers, Musicians, and Privates of Camp A, 8th Regiment U.S.C. Troops, do hereby acknowledge to have received of Capt. George E. Wagner the several articles of Clothing set opposite or respective names..." [66 names] 1864 Feb 2 (Folder 6)
- Provisional Commission, George E. Wagner, Major, 8th United States Colored Troops, signed Major General Benjamin F. Butler, Department of Virginia & North Carolina, [Army of the James], Fort Monroe, Virginia; attested by Assistant Adjutant-General Israel R. Sealy 1864 Sep 12 (Folder 6)
- Provisional Commission, George E. Wagner, Lieutenant Colonal, 9th United States Colored Troops, signed Major General Benjamin F. Butler, Department of Virginia & North Carolina, [Army of the James], Fort Monroe, Virginia; attested by Assistant Adjutant-General Israel R. Sealy 1864 Oct 21 (Folder 6)
- Commission, George E. Wagner, Colonel (brevet), "for gallant service and conduct at the battle of Olustee, Florida, and for meritorious service during the war," signed President Andrew Johnson amd Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton, Washington; bears notation "Recorded Volume 5, Page 18, Adjutant-General's Office/August 3, 1866" 1866 Aug 3 (Folder 6)